Certainly, presenting remotely raises some interesting variations on the classic techniques we’ve been talking about.
It’s not that anything you do in person that’s good becomes bad, but different things become more important.
You still need to think about: where is my audience? Where do I want them to be?
How do I connect with them emotionally? The empathy part of EPIC still holds true. And you still need to ask that question:
what do I want them to think or feel or do as a result of this conversation we’re having? What is the purpose
of meeting? And many of the techniques that work in a physical presentation will work in a virtual presentation, well — sometimes even better.
The camera imposes new challenges,
new opportunities. First of all, obviously, we’re seeing only a part of each person: we’re seeing their face mostly, and
the top half of their body. So it’s different from walking around on a stage.
Your body language, by contrast, needs to be a bit more restrained. It’s not going to help if you move around the place and waggle your arms a lot.
And strangely, if you use your body language in person, this looks fine, but on a camera you can start to look like you have giant hands.
So if you do move your hands, try to keep them a little bit more level, on the same plane as yourself physically.
Think also about the level of your camera. You want your camera to be roughly at eye level.
If it’s too high, you can start to look really small. And if it’s too low, people end up looking up your nose, and it looks like you think you’re terribly self-important.
And so a nice balance is good for that.
And finally, your eye contact works very strangely on camera. I’m sure you’ve worked this out already.
But when you actually look at the faces, it looks like you’re not making eye contact. Now that’s okay, people are used to it.
But if you have a really important key message to deliver, it’s worth looking direct at the camera and imagining the people behind that camera, because you will communicate more powerfully that way.
Finally, a typical pitfall is looking at yourself. Switch yourself off, so that you can concentrate on the other people on the call,
your audience — which is that third point of style, establishing the emotional connection.